This is the Genomic Research Agent
an entry for the AMD AI DevMaster Hackathon, Track 2.
It is an agentic AI for population genetics.
Everything you are about to see runs locally on an AMD Radeon 780M.
No API key.
No network call.
No per query billing.
And every number shown on screen is measured at run time
not printed from a string.
I want to start with verification rather than claims.
There are fifty five automated tests here
and they check real mathematical invariants rather than just whether the
code runs.
The eigenvector equation for the P C A solver.
F S T bounded between zero and one.
Minor allele frequency never above one half.
And agreement between the GPU and CPU implementations of the same statistic.
All fifty five pass, with zero compiler warnings.
Here are six natural language queries running through the agent.
Each one is routed by a custom Okapi B M twenty five kernel that I wrote
from scratch
with bigram features, dispatched as a compute shader on the AMD GPU.
Look at the relevance score printed beside every selected tool.
That means the routing is auditable rather than a black box.
Most agents do this step with a language model API call.
This one does not need a language model at all
so the core function has no network dependency and no cost.
Now the GPU benchmark.
The code explicitly enumerates graphics adapters and targets the AMD device
by its vendor I D
rather than accepting whichever GPU a generic high performance heuristic
would pick.
That matters on this machine, which also has a discrete card.
Every GPU result is cross checked against an independent CPU reference on
every single run.
The maximum observed difference is two millionths
which is floating point rounding and nothing more.
At the larger problem size the GPU path reaches three point four seven times
faster than CPU.
And notice that at the smaller size the CPU actually wins
because dispatch overhead has not amortized yet.
That is reported too, rather than quietly dropped.
This is a multi turn conversation.
Turn three is only four words: and its p value.
Term overlap scoring alone has essentially nothing to match on there.
Local conversation memory detects that it is a follow up
supplies the missing context from the previous turns
and it routes correctly back to the selection scan.
Concept questions are handled by local retrieval over a knowledge corpus
compiled into the binary
and it returns passages verbatim rather than generated text
so the answer is grounded in something you can go and read.
That retrieval runs through the same GPU kernel as the routing.
The same tools again
but now against a real bundled slice of the 1000 Genomes Project.
Three hundred real variants across one hundred real samples.
Real biology, real noise
and the full provenance of how that slice was derived is documented in the
repository.
One last thing, and it is the part I care about most.
On synthetic data the permutation test finds sixteen of five hundred markers
significant.
On the real 1000 Genomes data it finds zero.
That is genuine low statistical power at this sample size.
It is not a bug, and I kept it in the demo instead of hiding it
because a test that can never return a negative result is not really a test.
You can verify every claim in this project yourself in about two minutes by
running verify dot s h.
Thank you for watching.